this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program
[Music]
okay so welcome listeners to another
episode a new episode on software
engineering radio this time we talk with
John Wiegand about living architectures
so welcome John good to talk to you
Martin um it's great to have you on the
show would you introduce yourself to all
listeners tell us a little bit about
your background history and what are you
doing these days
very good so if I back up to the
beginning I started off as a small talk
programmer more than 20 years ago and
applied the small talk language to
working on embedded systems I was an
oscilloscope designer and transitioned
from that through a range of other
opportunities but switched from doing
application programming into developing
tools and so I built small talk tools
and then moved to building Java
development environments and from that I
into eclipse was involved in creating
the Eclipse platform and the
architecture underneath that and that
was really an interesting time and my
interest at that point then transitioned
into building community and did a did
work in establishing the Eclipse
consortium and then the Eclipse
Foundation getting the underpinnings of
the open source project the way we'd
like and that was a very important time
of learning both how good architectures
are helpful but also how they are
valuable in establishing ecosystem and
whole open environments anyway after
that my my next work and what I'm still
involved in today is instead of focusing
as much on desktop tools the focus is
what can we do
architectural II in terms of the server
based tools so again the similar thought
trying to build an architecture that
lets us bring a range of tools together
server based tools this time and allow
them to work together well so we provide
additional value to
who's ever putting these tools together
I transitioned again another dimension
of transition this is a more of a
personal observation went from leading
the development effort for some of the
first jazz based products I was leading
the rational team concert effort to a
role now as an architect looking at the
product portfolio and the I'll call it
the ecosystem issues but it's how we
defined something so that anyone can
build applications to this structure and
that's really my my focal point it's how
to be successful and enable success in
product integration you know it often
looks like we're talking about something
that's developer centric but really my
my focus is not just the inside
developer the people creating tools but
what are the characteristics of a
tooling environment that makes the
consumers of those tools effective and
then similarly what do we do in the
development side to make that possible
so that gives you just a quick quick
overview of the kinds of things I've
been up to lately
transitioning from a single language to
a supporting desktop tools over for a
range of different kinds of development
to now focusing on you know the broader
problems of team collaboration planning
planning the work tools for supporting
the development of the work and then the
testing aspects that that follow on
including to what happens after the
software is deployed being will have
traceability from the you know initial
concept all the way through to the
deployed software being able to track
you know things are successful things
that aren't successful and looking at
the whole development lifecycle today we
did we talked about living architectures
that's the title of a talk you gave it
eclipse come what do you mean by by
living architecture what is that well
instead of talking about an archetype
sure in particular there's a range of
different architectures that people use
and they're valuable for the individual
problems that they're solving but what I
was trying to get across with this
notion of living architectures is
characteristics of architectures that
are important at least for certain
systems so if you're building open
systems where you want to have a well
you need significant scalability you
need to be able to support a broad team
in fact team outside of the normal sense
where you have multiple organizations
involved you have all these dimensions
at once you need to be able to enable
multi-dimensional progress so what are
some characteristics of an architecture
that you need to be able to support this
kind of development and then the next
dimension is how do you support this
kind of develop and how do you create an
architecture when the requirements on
the architecture aren't known in advance
so you're working in this area where you
need to be able to adapt and evolve as
you go and be able to add more
capabilities to it so I coined this
phrase living architectures to refer to
an architecture that's set up to adapt
to the the changing demands or the
characteristics of an architecture that
we can put in place up front that will
help us do this and you know if I go
ahead and look at Eclipse and jazz as
two places where I've been involved in
this kind of thing that they both have
this characteristic so let me just use
both of those as examples so with
Eclipse what we established early on was
this plug-in architecture and what that
did that was a fundamental decision but
once we had that decision in place we
then enabled everyone to come to the
table and define their own plugins so
they could come in and define new
extension points new ways to extend the
system and with that simple notion that
that we established in the platform
proper we enabled this broad ecosystem
of progress so that's a case of a living
architecture we're much more was
possible
than was initially intended and it was
ready to adapt we can't even take credit
for all the things that that proved to
be possible because of that but that's
the door that we opened on the Jo side
it's a separate set of requirements that
we needed to be able to focus on and be
flexible with and what we're seeing in
the jazz world is there's a range of
server based technologies that are out
there today there's people building
things in c-sharp
there's Java development there's PHP and
more whole range of technologies and we
can't come up and say well the way to
build what you need is to work on any
given technology we need to focus on
integration so the living thought in the
jazz context is to focus on protocol
based integration defining in a language
neutral way what does it mean to
integrate and to define these restful
interfaces and by doing that the various
tool providers can implement the
interface in whatever language they like
as long as they support it and so this
is a case of another notion we don't
want to say living architectures will be
restful or living architectures or
things that follow the Eclipse plug-in
architecture it's more of this
classification scheme where we say a
living architecture is one that's
adaptable it allows progress to be
happening on multiple timelines it
allows new concepts to show show up
later and be able to put into the mix
and defining an architecture that's that
flexible that adaptable is is what I'm
calling a living architecture and it
matches nicely to these kind of agile
software development where you just
start small growing over time really
good point Martin so now we talk about
an architecture as a static thing
sometimes are we in our minds sometimes
think of an architecture as a problem
that's completely solved before we start
and then it's just a matter of execution
but reality is we need to be agile in
our architecture evolution as well and
this the thought here is if you have a
Living Architecture one
that's able to adapt your your in a
place to actually and to do that where
you can grow up and you can address new
needs and you can provide new concepts
that you didn't have have in place
initially when I talk to people about
this kind of having architecture is an
imagined space and you need to change
all the time
maybe sometimes argue that okay but you
cannot change everything you need to
make some decisions at the beginning and
follow those decisions you can't change
does everything easily within your
system how does it match to your let's
say living architectures I actually
agree with the point which is some
decisions that we make we put those in
place and you can't get out of them what
let's just go look at the two examples
I've already given us the Eclipse
plug-in architecture has a certain set
of characteristics if we came and said
we wanted to discard that notion and
replace it with a completely different
notion to plugin that could be done but
that's actually no longer an adaptation
of the Eclipse architecture that's
really a new architecture in that case
similarly on the Jazz side we could come
do something completely different but it
would be something completely different
the more fundamental notions that you
have in place and that you can stick to
it it actually enables a faster rate of
progress on these on the other
dimensions so there are things that are
difficult to move you know on the Jazz
side if we decided that what we really
would like would be something other than
focusing on restful interfaces that
would be a fundamental change which
would really cause us to unwind and
start over so those kind of things some
of these fundamental decisions cannot be
redone without them without a major
reset but but a lot of other decisions
can in the jazz world as we look at
providing additional services for new
ways of integration new ways of doing
cross-cutting query or a cross-cutting
notion of how projects should work
together those can those kind of things
can be layered on the system and we can
add those new notions as we go so there
are foundational elements that you're
stuck with in a good way
and then there's all
so the additional coloring in the system
that makes the system richer and more
powerful over time do you think it's
it's better to have a very very small
definition of the fundamentals so I
don't want to overstate this one but my
bias is towards a smaller set of core
concepts and then the remaining concepts
are things that are layered outside it
gives a lot more freedom both in the
immediate term it means you don't need
to be as far along to start but it also
lets you define new concepts and lose
the importance of old ones so there can
be something that you thought was a
fundamental importance at an early stage
that you realize really that didn't
matter as much if that was in the core
of the system then everybody's stuck
with that baggage but if it's something
that's on in the layering side you can
just quit leveraging it and move on so I
think the characteristics are better
when you can keep the the core concepts
to something that you can describe
though in a in a page or two or in a
five minute conversation versus
something that you need a study in depth
for you know for days or weeks on end
before you can get started how will you
describe the the Eclipse fundamental
architecture in five minutes
so the host fundamental architecture I
tried to give an overview of in just as
we started here it's a notion of we have
plugins plugins define extension points
and they can contribute to extension
points that someone else defined and
that's the whole that's the whole story
in addition there are some plugins that
are available for you to leverage to
build a desktop application and those
can be exploited but in terms of the
basic Eclipse architecture it's about
this thirty second two to one minute
story and you would add the Java
language to you or isn't it tight to
each other the Java language is how we
implemented our plugins so I would
actually not focus on the Java language
when I spoke immediately in fact in our
early days of eclipse we we in the back
of our mind imagined that you could be
implementing plugins in any language now
it turns out we never did
go ahead and enable that and it would be
more work more than more than a little
bit of work but in terms of describing
the story the Java language is an
implementation detail an important one
because it's what we're working with and
the frameworks that are available are
Java centered but in terms of just
understanding the concept if if I was
trying to talk to another software
developer and give them the flavor of it
I would talk about the notion of plugins
independent of Java before I came back
and filled in the the Java
implementation point okay and how would
you describe the jazz architecture in
five minutes
so the jazz architecture is based on the
architecture of the web so if you have
the architecture of the web in mind you
have a good underpinning so look at the
world of linked data instead of linked
webpages
so the various artifacts that your
software development environment works
with things from things from planning
through to requirements your your plans
the test cases that you're building your
at this is the source code itself all
these pieces are resources that we
establish a URL for and then we
establish relationships we do
relationships with just in our content
having a reference to the the other
artifacts so that's the basic story of
the link data then we have a range of
services that we can provide we've
defined a set of domain services and
we've done that in an open way at open
services net those interfaces define
what does it mean to integrate with a
change management system or a
requirements management system or a
quality management system those can be
implemented by any tool in any language
in addition we have a set of integration
services this is just another dimension
integration services let us have a
cross-cutting notion of what does it
mean to be part of a project or how did
a query across all these tools
so just to circle back and tell the
whole story
we have integration services that are
provided by Jaz and then we have this
notion of open services which are the
domain services that can be implemented
by any tool and they hold the old
services are based in it restful style
absolutely so we've taken a restful
approach for all the services that we're
building what role does the the let's
say more lies in the rest of all things
it's even called old-fashioned but what
about API design so even if you use
rescue still have some kind of API some
kind of semantics for servers and things
like that what what do you think what
role does API design has in in the chess
world or the chest living architecture
style yeah so so when you take a restful
approach on that that's a style of doing
development but it we can't discount the
need of having well-defined interfaces
even if we're working in a restful way
for working in other more traditional
ways we can actually establish horrible
restful interfaces it you can do you can
build things that are tightly coupled
you can leak too many concepts you can
muddle the consumer versus the provider
notions and get those basically
integrated together in bad ways so the
notion of doing solid API design
understanding what the concepts are who
the who the consumer of the interface is
who the provider is and getting that in
the right place is really important and
so I think API design continues to be an
important skill and something that we
need to take diligent care to regardless
of our architectural approach um do you
think that the the way you design API is
is different in the westphall world than
in a traditional let's say Java API
framework world there are differences
they you need we you need to look at
things differently the traditional
framework solution focuses on
the the call chain much more centrally
and the data becomes something that gets
carried along I'm speaking in broad
generalities we're in a restful approach
the real focus is on understanding the
concepts and making sure you get the
right resources in in place and that's
the central the central focus so it's a
different mindset
and so it takes practice at getting used
to it but the importance of having a
good interface applies just as well on
in both cases you think that this kind
of architecture is somehow moving back
from the object-oriented willed back
into some kind of data centric world
well part of that is true there's some
there's some truth in that observation
Martin but I don't overplay it with the
java language is going to continue to be
valuable as our range of other languages
that are going to have object-oriented
characteristics but in terms of
establishing these loosely coupled
architectures the the boundary that you
want when your language neutral likely
doesn't want to talk about notions like
inheritance it really wants to focus on
what is the data and how does it connect
and then enable a range of ways for that
data to be exposed you think that the
typical framework API is we use
inheritance and stuff like that and are
then let's say reduced to the
implementation of specific services and
not so important anymore in your whole
architecture so I would say that they're
locally important so in terms of the
cross-cutting interfaces what's exposed
at the language neutral protocol level I
don't think we want to be able we don't
want to talk inheritance at that level
is my my bias however when you're
providing implementation frameworks and
toolkits there's a whole range of
elements that we have in those those
toolkits and the characteristics of the
language that we're using is is
something that we would tap into
so in in that regard we would be
leveraging libraries we'd create
frameworks there would be we just
naturally get code sharing through some
of the usages of inheritance and just
the shoring to design of those toolkits
so I think they're a complimentary
notion where we don't try to have the
whole world talk in terms of
object-oriented concepts but in local
local toolkits we still leverage that
let's say I would like to start a
project what do you think which would be
the first steps I really would like to
do some kind of living architecture I
would be flexible because I do some
agile development and what would your
advice be to me well I draw attention to
a few things and given I'm haven't
really put together the canonical list
here I'm sure I'll miss some of the
important notions but starting with a
strong team people with strong design
and implementation skills both I think
is a really important characteristic is
a strong team that can really make
things happen
then establishing a common view of the
goal that you're trying to achieve and a
shared view of this core architecture
the what are we going to treat as
bedrock once you have those two
characteristics so you have a strong
team that can really make things happen
that has this shared view of the goal
even if imprecise in terms of all the
characteristics you're now set up to
work in an agile way of making it happen
and then iterating on both the the
layered part of the architecture but but
also on proving that the problems that
you're solving are are meeting the the
customer need so being able to work on
both of those dimensions at once I think
it really important people like me you
know I have this architecture title I
believe that people like me are really
have a support role in this versus the
central role the central role is a
strong team with great design skills and
do it skills and when you can have bring
that together with a view of where
you're going
good things will happen so it sounds
like you you are helping out the team
should do that stuff currently that's
mine my role is to help clarify the
goals so we're all pushing the same way
join in on some of the problem-solving
as part of the team when given an
opportunity I both enjoy that and have a
little bit to contribute but I really do
think of my role as one of helping help
helping the teams and the efforts work
effectively you know in the past I spent
a fair bit of time in the in the Eclipse
world we talked about the architecture
of Eclipse then we spent a lot of time
talking about how we built Eclipse and
what does it mean to do effective
software development I consider my
current role even if my title is as an
architect really has those same
characteristics helping to define the
architecture but also then working how
how can people use that architectural
definition to help build effective
software how to make your your project
the individual pieces work more
effectively and what do you think of the
most common problems that you see when
you help people well I'm kind of
belaboring one point so I'll mention it
and maybe something also come to mind
subsequently one of the big problems is
not having a clear picture of what the
problem is so a vague impression of the
assignment versus a more precise one
just because it's for a range of reasons
sometimes the problems aren't are well
defined in advanced other other times
people have a pain point so they have a
specific pain point but they haven't
articulated the solution so that effort
of translating from a difficulty a pain
point into what should be done is is
always hard just to get that right
that's that's something that's that's
just a challenge the other thing that I
do see is we have a lot of skills in
object-oriented design and we have less
experience to date but it's growing you
know over the last few years the
industry as a whole we've we've built up
a body of expertise but I know that it
uniformly we're not there as
yet so it takes a little bit of an
additional effort to get a good resource
design in place so I see those what the
one high-level problem of making sure
that you're you're doing the right thing
and then I guess the the detail problem
that I would flag would be practice in
the resource design the ongoing effort
for the tools to continue to support the
effort better and you know the the
industry is moving the tools forward but
I think there's room for even further
improvement there and and everyone's
working on it I don't wanna go any
particulars on that point but better
tooling is always helpful
the second point always wrong reminds me
on all my time at the university where
the people told me updated on your
programming and say oh please don't
focus on the data the data is hidden and
then secret inside the object so focus
on the behavior and on the API and now I
see this is slightly moving towards okay
behavior knob trainer and stuff it's
very important for building stuff but
for designing the api's the data comes
more into to the center of interest it's
I think it's pretty interesting it is
let me actually tell you a story about
it and I think it makes it pretty easy
to picture so I won't speak about any
program in in the universe but if you
look at what it means with respect to
software tools
um we're building a range of tools but
what the tools are doing is they're
manipulating the data they're
manipulating the requirements the test
cases the work items and the source code
well when all is said and done the fact
that you had tools to work with that is
somewhat interesting but this data that
you created the understanding the set of
requirements in the test cases and
having the code artifact that's
something that's going to live a long
time and so being able to have that data
independent of the tools and be able to
work with it and analyze it understand
it is really important and something
that we really in terms of software
tooling architectures really hadn't paid
as much attention to in the past where
we're really focusing I would say on the
tools first
and then as a side effect they produce
some data and what we're paying
attention to more now is that data is
really important and the tools work and
manipulate that data so they're
complimentary but they're both important
I'm coming back to the other point you
mentioned about is difficult to find the
right the right gold and the right
transition from what is a pain point and
how to transform it into some kind of
solution or something that helps you um
how do you think what can help me to
figure out that I'm on the right path
while doing this transition so I have
two two reactions to it so the first is
making sure that you motivate the
problem that you're working on the the
next increment to the system on solving
a specific problem so doing something
with a story in mind to say this is the
capability we're providing not we're
adding this feature we're adding feature
ex-dad feature X but we're doing it
because we're addressing this pain point
because if we're doing it for that
reason then we actually have a
checkpoint at the end of the iteration
to say well have we helped the user out
who's in that situation have we
addressed their pain and we can get
their feedback on it and if we happen to
be the user ourselves we can sulfus us
if you're just adding a feature the only
conclusion you can make is yes I did
something but you can't it's really
difficult to get your hands around well
how much progress am i making towards
solving a real problem and so I really
think to focus on a specific use case to
address a specific pain point is a
really important mindset to have when
when doing new work its features don't
provide value its solutions capability
provided that together addresses a
problem is what what our users want to
need when I think about these putting
this into relation to typical a child
evelopment where people say okay do a
short iteration and put the system into
production right away right after the
iteration to get feedback if that really
solves a problem in the real world
would you agree and how would how long
with these kind of cycles or how long do
you and do you create these kind of
feedback cycles putting the system in
protection so I agree that theoretical
feedback or hypothetical feedback or we
hope it solves the problem is is not
helpful so we want to get it you know
the pieces we build in front of our
customers and I encourage everyone to do
that kind of thing this the cycles we've
been working in our four-week cycles we
found that works pretty well I know some
prefer shorter cycles yet and I and I
can understand that it depends on the
degree of distribution of the
development team the more co-located the
team is I believe you can shrink the
cycles to even shorter but if you're
working on an open source project or in
a another project where that the teams
are distributed around the world the
additional time is at least for us has
proven to be helpful to get through the
effort of putting together a plan for
the iteration and doing the development
work for it and validating along the way
and then getting it out for people to
put to use so in ours for weeks we've
done six weeks in the past but that kind
of iteration feels feels pretty good for
for our experience and if you put things
out in full week cycles um is it really
for for end-users doing their daily
business with that tool well we did get
that in the Eclipse world that the teams
were adopting it at that cycle what
we're seeing with some of our newer
tools is people pick up these iterations
they don't pick them all up so the
customers aren't interested in changing
their server based infrastructure every
four weeks but a set of our users pick
up some of every milestones right so we
get some feedback all the time and in
addition to our own internal consumption
so in the case of the rational team
concert and the other jazz products that
rationals building we're actually
building those and deploying them for
internal
sumption on that regular basis and and
our customers are deploying it you know
some of the milestones but not all okay
so you're also in this very very nice
situation where you can eat your own dog
food and learn learn yourself what
you've built
do you also help teams not produced in
developer tools but producing suffer
solutions for people not doing self
development well yeah we we believe that
the Jazz tools are are valuable in
general the question that we need to ask
there is so milestone based development
is still a valuable thing but the
question again that we want to ask is
what's the best way to get the customer
feedback in those loops and whether it's
making your content available
continuously updating your your your web
in real time well you know basically
you're in continuous delivery mode which
is a highly successful approach it just
depends on the specific that the the
customers engaged in but still the story
of milestone based development building
your interations and getting feedback on
them at as regularly as possible I think
it's just a good thing if you look back
over the past and I'm not sure you mean
you must be involved in this jazz and
eclipse technology for 10 years and so
if you look back over the past 10 years
what would you do differently if you
would start let's say Java based IDE or
the Eclipse platform today on the
Eclipse IDE Eclipse has been more
successful than I would have ever hoped
and we we had fond ambitions of how
things could go but I would have never
expected this things to go this broadly
there's a few things I would have I
would consider doing differently but
they're more they're more fine-tuning I
would really at this point even in
hindsight be reticent to to do anything
that would have caused the adoption to
be less than it is so the one thing that
I think could have been helpful is to
see a few more projects earlier
in in the effort so we had the platform
early with the Java development tools
and the PDE there then we we established
a technology incubator and and another
tools project to try a few other things
out I think it would been valuable in
those early days to have a few more
initiatives going on at the same time
just to try more things make go even
broader and learn more and and that's
where we're at today at Eclipse where
eclipse just has a large norm project I
think we could have bootstrap the
ecosystem a little bit if we could have
got there sooner so I think we could
have made even more progress if that
could have been the case and from the
architectural point of view
architectural II I'm pretty happy again
I think the risk of doing something
different is greater than the value that
be provided there's some fine-tuned
maybe some bugs in the way the the
plug-in activation worked I think
there's some refinements that we could
do in that area that would make things
better but that's entirely secondary to
the overall structure the story we tell
about plugins with extension points I
think was a really nice story tapping
into some of the characteristics of the
web which is going now I think makes
good sense but ten years ago in the
early Eclipse days that wouldn't have
been a good good investment and the
importance of having solid desktop tools
I think it's still there
so again I'm pretty happy with the the
set of trade-offs that that we as a
community made around eclipse and the
opportunities that we've opened now and
you look back over the past use of the
Jazz development so on the Jazz side I
have a similar attention we really
didn't start with the architecture of
the web we started on this exercise of
exploring and seeing what's possible in
terms of collaboration we learned a lot
there and I think that was really
important I would have appreciated it if
we had have seen that we wanted to go to
the web architecture a bit earlier but I
will put a caveat in place on this so I
have been used
to have that so we could have been
starting to think and adopt some of
those thoughts but one of the challenges
that happens in systems is if you make
the initial amount of work on too much
invention or the development team that
you have working on it and things aren't
clearly enough articulated it actually
does cause a little bit of swirling
going on in those early days so in
hindsight on the jazz side I would have
liked to have had a little bit more of
the web thinking in at the early day so
I think that have been valuable to us
and but the other aspect of doing the
prototyping the exploration and the
learning the way you get to a place to
really understand what does
collaboration mean I think that was
great and I wouldn't do anything to
undermine that part and looking today
the architecture of the jazz system with
the web I could take tree in style you
would do exactly the same again right
yeah so I'm really pleased with that I
would say right now we're in the the
layering part of it so we've we now have
described and defined the architecture
we've built the core pieces and we're
refining those or in the place now of
doing that layering and we're really
happy with where we're at in terms of
our core and now it's the I'll call it
the fun part of building the the layers
around it to to make it more valuable
and to enable greater degrees of
integration you briefly mentioned the
the it's just just a site right now and
the importance of desktop tools do you
think that that's still the case today
so I believe there's a range of tools
that people want and in today's
development if you're doing Java
programming or you're doing other you're
building in c-sharp will say C++ desktop
development tools and integrated
development environment feel it is
really valuable and I think that's going
to continue for some time there's a
range of other interactions though that
developers have where we're doing a lot
of work around planning what we're doing
is breaking down our work into the
various sub pieces and you know kicking
off a build and tracking our build
quality
and trying to look at how these things
connect it's not clear to me in fact
it's pretty clear that desktop tools
aren't required for all that work so I
think what we're in right now is this
hybrid environment where the desktop
tool is valuable for the heavy
development effort the heavy coding
debugging effort but as you broaden out
and consider some of the other aspects
of the lifecycle especially around the
the planning and the the tracking
aspects of it the the web is becoming
increasingly promising and what I think
over time there will be more and more
aspects of our problem solved in the web
and I don't want to say when we'll get
to the place where where everything
perhaps goes there but but I believe
that's the trend that more and more and
over the next decade will we'll learn
more about that I think I heard that
Java is still the the main language
you're using for your tool development
these days but do you think that will
change in the near future well - two
things I can imagine happening so I Java
is gonna continue for for a significant
period of time we both have an extensive
code base today and I can see us will
continue to augment elaborate that and
we'll go there so I see that continuing
for for several years but the the
growing use of JavaScript and dojo and
some of the other technologies that fit
into the the web-centric space those are
going to continue to grow in popularity
and usefulness and there will be both
tooling support to make us more
effective using those things so the
additional libraries created and they're
probably new new extensions you know as
we see html5 grow up we'll be able to
tap into that more and more so I think
we'll see a lot going there - to
complement what we've done in the past
just in working in Java
could you imagine implementing a whole
IDE environment in JavaScript I can't
imagine it today but that'll be an
interesting question for us to ask down
the road you know are there things that
can we can do to evolve the capability
there so today it's not even imaginable
but there's partial interfaces that
kangri created in JavaScript that are
that are pretty impressive so I think
we'll see more and more happening and
we'll see what the breakthroughs are
that they get us to the next level there
so I think yeah we we get good
impression what do you think about
living architectures and we talk a
little a lot about these kind of agile
software development I think so any
other let's say pearls of wisdom you
would like to share with our listeners
Martin I think you've emptied the store
of ideas from me for this morning what I
what I'd like to do is encourage people
to to think about this this observation
when it's applicable right if you're in
a constrained problem traditional
thoughts on architectures makes full
sense but when you think about these
open adaptable evolving systems
hopefully we triggered some some
thoughts for people to absorb and I'd
like to hear about other applications of
this thought so people are digging into
in their own areas and if these this
approach and these styles are resonating
I'd love to hear more about it and see
if there's more than just a nugget here
but something that's broadly applicable
great John thank you very very much for
spending the time to talk with us it was
a great session and thank you very much
thanks Martin take care take care Thanks
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineering
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at SE - radio dotnet if you want to
support us you can donate to the SU
radio team by our website or you can
advertise for su radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash dot button to
contact the team please send email to
team at s e - radio net or it is
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pot site Music
Network for the music used in this show
the song is called Vegas Achtung
[Music]
you